Guide to the Ray K. Metzker photographs, 1957-1982 RL.11872
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Ray K. Metzker photographs
1957-1982
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Metzker, Ray K.
RL.11872
1.0 Linear Feet 2 boxes 20 photographic prints
Ray K. Metzker (1931-2014) was an American photographer based in Philadelphia. The twenty black-and-white photographs in the collection were taken by Metzker from 1957 to 1982. The subjects are chiefly city streets, beaches, and landscapes; they all feature the strong, sometimes abstract, light and dark compositions that Metzker was known for. Locations are unidentified, but may include the New Jersey Shore; Philadelphia; Chicago; and Germany and other locations in Europe. The gelatin silver prints come in two sizes: 8x10 (17) and 11x14 (3) inches. All of the prints are marked on the versos with the photographer's archive stamp, and include various legacy identifiers, edition numbers, and printing dates. Acquired as part of the Archive of Documentary Arts at Duke University.
Biographical / Historical
Ray K. Metzker was born in 1931 and lived most of his adult life in Philadelphia, Pennsylvania. He attended graduate school at the Institute of Design in Chicago, where he studied with Harry Callahan and Aaron Siskin. He was known for his bold black-and-white photography, and for his modernist style, particularly in his use of dark and light to create photographic expression. He died in 2014 in Philadelphia.
Arrangement
The prints in this collection are ordered by date, in the sequence assigned by the donor.
Conditions Governing Access
Collection is open for research.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The Ray K. Metzker photographs were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in 2020.
Related Materials
Aaron Siskind photographs of Harlem, circa 1933-1941
Scope and Contents
The collection comprises twenty black-and-white silver gelatin prints of images taken from 1957 to 1982 by American photographer Ray K. Metzker. The subjects chiefly feature city streets, beaches, and landscapes; they all feature the strong, sometimes abstract, light and dark compositions that Metzker was known for. Locations are unidentified, but may include the New Jersey Shore; Philadelphia; Chicago; and Germany and other locations in Europe.
The prints come in two sizes: 8x10 (17) and 11x14 (3) inches, with a few minor variations. All of the prints are marked on the versos with the photographer's archive stamp, and include legacy identifiers, edition numbers, and printing dates.
The donor's inventory as well as the photographer's published work and exhibits provided the source for titles and original negative dates.
Beaches -- Photographs; Black-and-white photography -- 20th century; Documentary Photography -- United States; Photographers -- Pennsylvania -- Philadelphia; Street photography; Urban life -- Photographs; Europe -- Photographs; United States -- Social life and customs -- 20th century; Black-and-white prints (photographs); Gelatin silver prints; Archive of Documentary Arts (Duke University); Metzker, Ray K.
- Photographs, 1957-1982
  Scope and Contents
  Prints are arranged in date order, as sequenced in the donor inventory. All prints are marked on the backs with the photographer's archive authentication stamp, and include edition numbers, legacy identifiers, and print dates. Image titles consist of letter-number codes assigned by the photographer, with the first digits apparently indicating the original negative date; these titles appear in published works and exhibits. A brief content description is included in library staff notes. The locations are unidentified on these prints, but the beach scenes are almost certainly part of Metzker's "Sand Creatures" portfolio, approximately 1968-1977.
  - 57 CD-10, 1957; Gelatin silver print. Dimensions: 8 x 10 inches. (Box 1, Print RL.11872-P-0001)
    Narrow passageway between buildings, location probably Europe.
  - 58 AD-10, 1958; Gelatin silver print. Dimensions: 10 x 8 inches. (Box 1, Print RL.11872-P-0002)
    Broken black umbrella.
  - 61 L-83, 1961; Gelatin silver print. Dimensions: 7 x 9 3/8 inches. (Box 1, Print RL.11872-P-0003)
    Location probably Spain. Amputee on crutches entering streetfront building.
  - 61 DL-2, 1961; Gelatin silver print. Dimensions: 7 7/8 x 9 7/8 inches. (Box 1, Print RL.11872-P-0004)
    Storefront on street in Germany.
  - 63 HQ-7, 1963; Gelatin silver print. Dimensions: 8 x 9 7/8 inches. (Box 1, Print RL.11872-P-0005)
    Woman walking on street, figured in far right corner of frame.
  - 64 CU-40, 1964; Gelatin silver print. Dimensions: 8 x 9 7/8 inches. (Box 1, Print RL.11872-P-0006)
    Large black car and passengers on city street.
  - 64 IO-11, 1964; Gelatin silver print. Dimensions: 8 x 9 7/8 inches. (Box 1, Print RL.11872-P-0007)
    Man behind wheel of large light car with markings on windshield.
  - 65 HS-12, 1965; Gelatin silver print. Dimensions: 7 7/8 x 10 inches. (Box 1, Print RL.11872-P-0008)
    Old man walking on city street by large building with fallout shelter sign above him.
  - 67 BU-6, 1967; Gelatin silver print. Dimensions: 7 7/8 x 10 inches. (Box 1, Print RL.11872-P-0009)
    Bread truck in traffic in snowy street.
  - 68 DZ, 1968; Gelatin silver print. Dimensions: 10 x 8 inches. (Box 1, Print RL.11872-P-0010)
    Abstract, narrow image of pine tree.
  - 70 AJ-1, 1970; Gelatin silver print. Dimensions: 10 x 8 inches. (Box 1, Print RL.11872-P-0011)
    Woman in light dress sitting on low wall with Philadelphia's Independence Hall in background.
  - 71 JA-43, 1971; Gelatin silver print. Dimensions: 8 x 9 7/8 inches. (Box 1, Print RL.11872-P-0012)
    Three shadowy figures standing in ocean surf. Printed 1976.
  - 75 BQ-24, 1975; Gelatin silver print. Dimensions: 10 x 8 inches. (Box 1, Print RL.11872-P-0013)
    Close up of figure in beach chair.
  - 75 BQ-5A, 1975; Gelatin silver print. Dimensions: 8 x 9 7/8 inches. (Box 1, Print RL.11872-P-0014)
    Woman with large hat lying face down on beach towel.
  - 75 DB-9, 1975; Gelatin silver print. Dimensions: 8 x 9 7/8 inches. (Box 1, Print RL.11872-P-0015)
    Shadow of person on sand and another person's legs walking past beach towel.
  - 75 DE-8, 1975; Gelatin silver print. Dimensions: 8 x 9 7/8 inches. (Box 1, Print RL.11872-P-0016)
    Beach towel with sandals and empty beach chair. Printed 1979.
  - 75 DI-34, 1975; Gelatin silver print. Dimensions: 8 x 10 inches. (Box 1, Print RL.11872-P-0017)
    Woman standing in shallow ocean water, taken towards urban shoreline with large buildings.
  - 81 IQ-19, 1981; Gelatin silver print. Dimensions: 11 x 14 inches. (Box 2, Print RL.11872-P-0018)
    Shadowy figure with highlights on arm and sneakers. Printed 1982.
  - 82 HQ-43, 1982; Gelatin silver print. Dimensions: 10 7/8 x 13 7/8 inches. (Box 2, Print RL.11872-P-0019)
    Woman with shopping bag walking on street, towards camera. Printed 2006.
  - 82 IU-44, 1982; Gelatin silver print. Dimensions: 11 x 13 7/8 inches. (Box 2, Print RL.11872-P-0020)
    Small figure peering through large dark glass façade. Printed 1983.